<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.9.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2023-05-17T00:35:01+04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">zeligism</title><subtitle>Academic Website. Includes some of my personal writing.</subtitle><author><name>Abdulla Jasem Almansoori</name></author><entry><title type="html">test</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2023/01/01/Empty.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="test" /><published>2023-01-01T04:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2023-01-01T04:00:00+04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2023/01/01/Empty</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2023/01/01/Empty.html">&lt;p&gt;\(E = mc^2\).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/einstein.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;image tooltip here&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdulla Jasem Almansoori</name></author><summary type="html">\(E = mc^2\).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Consistency</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/02/Consistency.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Consistency" /><published>2022-03-02T02:18:19+04:00</published><updated>2022-03-02T02:18:19+04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/03/02/Consistency</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/03/02/Consistency.html">&lt;p&gt;The idea of a world view in AI is very important. If you want to simulate an autonomous agent that interacts with the world in a non-trivial manner, then we can say that the agent has to maintain a “world-view”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;world-view&quot;&gt;World-view&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This world-view should contain as much info about the world as possible in order to be efficient—maybe even the entire history of the observations of the world in case memory is limitless. However, not only is memory storage a constraint, but so are memory access and computing power. If memory is limitless somehow, then can we really access it efficiently? Can we take a memory and process it within the agent in a meaningful duration of time? It might be theoritcally possible using some abstract mathematical model that we are not aware of. Assuming memory storage is finite, memories can be further compressed and indexed as they are stored. Compression is obviously an advantage when memory is finite, and indexing is natural given that we need to access memories somehow (and not necessarily access them exactly). So, how are memories compressed and indexed, then? One thing for sure is that context can play a key role in these two processes. I believe an important part of memory (all of it?) is stored in a sequential or programmatic manner, i.e. large memories are compressed as the output of much shorter programs. This way, you can compress infinite strings into a finite program (i.e. algorithm). Heck, there is no such thing as an infinite string that cannot be stored as the output of some program. To see how this is true, think about how you would describe writing your infinite string. Then, your description itself is the program (or the constraints of an implied program understood from context) that generates this infinite string. This is an interesting observation because we could imagine an infinite string that is indescribable in finite words or self-destructive in some sense (self-contradictory, for example), but remember that such strings are not “computable” so they are not the output of a meaningful program. (I’m not well-versed in theoretical computer science, so I could be wrong.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;programs&quot;&gt;Programs&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you introduce programs, you will then have to introduce interpreters because the same program can be interpreted differently by different agents. When it comes to language, the interpretation is up to the community of agents that is using it. Language construction and interpretation is distributed in some sense; it is not local to a single agent and it evolves as a whole within all the participating agents together as there is no single truth to language interpretation. This allows language to be stable and well-interpretable among the majority of agents without having a central authority on language. This could be the case under some assumptions, of course. It could be the case because knowledge about language is communicated regularly among all of the agents and large variations are usually suppressed (frowned upon, actually) or just slightly adjusted on the go. Even though adjustments are local to the agent (the feedback comes only from the neighboring agents in the communication network), the agents could potentially converge to approximately the same knowledge at the end. (I don’t have a proof for that, but I believe it’s possible to prove it given some additional technical assumptions. For example, one assumption could be the maintenance of a grammar by the community using that language.) In the same manner, we can have a distributed kind of memory that can process some form of a program description in a distributed way, and then generate outputs independently, verify the outputs, and then adjust interpretation through consensus. The interpretation should be able to reconstruct the relevant parts of the sensory inputs (or an intermediary description of it) as perfectly as possible. This compression / interpretation process can be hierarchical such that it is multi-step and intermediary results can be used in other processes. Once the agents reach a stable compression-interpretation scheme, they can store memories as accurately as possible in the shortest form possible. What remains is accessing this particular memory through an index.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;its-all-a-dream&quot;&gt;It’s All a Dream&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Indexing is the context-relevant part of the story. When we say “index”, we’re not really talking about a number, or a memory address. We’re talking about a signal that evokes a memory in a smooth manner given some memory state (slightly changing the signal given that memory state can still evoke similar kinds of memories). The signal could be a picture of a scene that you saw or a specific tone you heard during that memory you want to retrieve. Recalling a memory is not all obvious, as we seem to be able to recall memories without a reconstructable internal brain activity/signal. I might be wrong, especially if that internal signal could be exactly described somehow by the person, in which case there does exist a reconstructable brain signal (think about a neuron that represents a very specific property). Recalling a memory is similar to a program that runs in the brain—a search program, to be specific—so it is not all that different from other “programs” running in the brain. So far, terms like “program”, “description” , and “algorithm” seem to be describing the same phenomenon in the brain. The brain has an automatic recall feature, where a sensation can involuntarily remind you of something correlated with it, potentially completely irrelevant or just relevant to either the sensation or the context or their combination. This feature can be exploited to perform a sort of a progressively-selective indexing routine. We can start with a seed signal (a sensation, a thought, or a memory) and start actively recalling memories from that seed, and then select the relevant memories and try to recall finer details in the same fashion iteratively until we converge to what we believe to be the target memory we want to recall (which might not necessarily be an actual memory that we had but a made up one that was formed through a brainwash. You first have to believe that you can recall the target memory—that it is in your brain— given some sort of a “meta-description/signal” of it, which can be vague or wrong. You can’t recall a memory that didn’t happen, so you generate it and thus know that it is fake. But wouldn’t recalling a memory that have indeed happened be the same? Don’t we simply “re-generate” actual memories while assuming that they are real?)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;guts&quot;&gt;Guts&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This convergence process is clearly not as simple as it sounds as there are no guarantees that it can happen in finite time given the conditions described. One way we can enforce convergence to this recall process is to evaluate the relevance of the memory we recalled. The memory could be very relevant, and may as well feel like it’s true in the sense that it happened—or is just true by gut feeling. This “gut feeling”, I believe, is the qualia byproduct of the evaluation mechanism that estimates the convergence of the recall process, or simply estimates the truthiness of a thought. If your gut feeling is a conflicted and uneasy feeling, then you’re brain is basically saying that you haven’t converged to a stable memory or state of mind given the query you’re evaluating (recalling a memory or resolving the meaning and implication of a particular statement, for instance.) A strong gut feeling will tell you that you have a strong instinctive reason to believe in the result of your query. The query is the source of conflict that was introduced either by yourself or by an external source of information. Further explaining and understanding the emergence of this gut feeling, beyond the fact that it feels as elementary as the sense of a smell or a color, is completely out of my expertise. But the creation of a query that provokes gut feeling could probably be only associated with (or evoked by) native instinctive needs such as curiosity, survival, reproduction, etc. These instinctive needs could have probably been achieved via evolution—or perhaps by something more structured and elaborate. Who knows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;time-devours-life&quot;&gt;Time Devours Life&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ok, so far, we have tried to describe the concept of a world-view in an intelligent agent and how the agent can access information from it, but we haven’t yet explained anything about the dynamics of this procedure. For example, how does the world-view changes with each access or with time? Can we assume that the brain has the same structure and that it processes two consecutive “moments” in the same exact manner? The brain does have the ability to tell which moment came before, what happened and what didn’t, what might happen, and what might have happened if something else happened, which is like peeking into another timeline where such a thing did actually happen. But I believe that the brain does not have a “clock”, so to speak. It only creates chains of events that are marked by their temporal positions with respect to some significant event of which the date or timestamp had been explicitly memorized (e.g. your birth, your school years, etc.). Sometimes, it’s difficult to recall which year a particular event happened in your life, or whether one event happened before the other (think about what year in college you took a particular course, or how fast time moves in some scenarios vs. how slow it seems to move in others). The temporal order is only relevant when there is an interesting pattern. Who cares whether you yawned or scratched your head and whether you did it before brushing your teeth or after before sleeping. These are very trivial events that could be totally forgotten about and perhaps even believed to have not happened at all when asked about—let alone give their temporal order—and, surely, absolutely nothing will change in case you remembered the temporal order of these events, unless someone recorded that information and decided to quiz you on it for a million dollar (damn, that would totally suck). Seems like time is only important in the sense that it can only be “consumed” by “going forward”, and what is left behind in the back is something that “happened” for sure, regardless of which came before which (that would be figured out by the brain if it had been important). Thinking about it poetically, it is like time consumes the future and generates observables, which are the only things that we know that “are” for sure. Everything else is uncertain in this world. Even the things that we observe are only as good as our observations themselves, whether they are sense data or measurements. It is much like the process of discovering a mathematical theorem. I mean, that’s why it’s called “discovering a theorem” because it was already there and we just merely observed that it is consistent with our axioms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;consistency&quot;&gt;Consistency&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now if you connect the whole thing together and try to squeeze it all into one grand picture, you do get some fundamental ideas behind the maintenance of a world-view. We said that memories could be seen as distributed programs that take a seed signal or a description and produce a sequence of signals. The signals converge if the memory exists and can be recalled, where convergence is evaluated by gut feeling. Also, there is no explicit temporal ordering in this world-view. The sequence of signals produced in this process dictates the temporal order, not the other way around. So what do we take from that? Probably the fact that “consistency” is key. Consistency is paramount to world-view, probably for the same reason that it is for math, science, and any other discipline that is based on axiomatic principles. Without consistency, memories cannot be compressed well and cannot be recalled reliably. Also, without consistency, temporal order would be distorted and probably collapse. So what we can take away is that the world-view is maintained by minimizing inconsistencies as much as possible, where inconsistencies can be succinctly defined as “contradictory observations”, e.g. observations that say that such and such has the property of being something and not being it. These are usually found in the edge cases, where prior knowledge have to be refined in order to maintain consistency. Inconsistencies can be dealt with either by deleting one observation—acknowledging the fact that we observed wrongly—or by “adding”  details to the observations (e.g. adding conditions, “something is X at one moment, but could be Y at another”). Proceeding like this, our world-view becomes more and more consistent, allowing us to have a better expectation of the future (which might be one of the main objectives of the brain). This is assuming we live in a stable, consistent world (well, as long we have science and not magic, I guess we do).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;self-consistency&quot;&gt;“Self”-Consistency&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We still haven’t attempted to explain the way agents should interact with the world given this world-view, and why the heck people have different world-views if the process of maintaining one is as simple as “eliminate inconsistencies”. Well, to answer the second question first, it is because of the gut feeling-like factors that are controlled by genetics, as well as the process of inconsistency elimination itself. People can eliminate inconsistencies differently, and sometimes even still achieve the same world-view. So the interesting question is how agents interact with the world. This is a very interesting question, and it is perhaps the crux of this essay, despite being not so central to the idea of a world-view per se. This is what I believe:
&lt;strong&gt;Agents interact with the world in a manner that maintains their world-view consistency&lt;/strong&gt;.
There is nothing particularly deep about that statement, I know, but I do think it’s deep. The reason why I think it’s deep is because in this framework, it seems like the agent’s identity is intertwined with the world’s identity, so the agent sees itself as a “thing” in this world: a thing which it could completely control, much like peeping into the world through a spiritual hole which is the “self”, or, put simply, “playing a video game”. The existence of the source of decisions and the engine of our interactions can literally be anywhere. It only needs this channel which is somewhere in the brain. It might even be the case that all consciousnesses exist in a realm where they are somehow interconnected. Sure, that’s stepping into sci-fi territory, but prove me wrong. Looking at it this way, you start to feel kinda detached from your worldly “self”. The brain has full control of what happens in the world, but doesn’t have full control of its inputs—the inputs that come from that thing over there in the realm of “free will”, consciousness, and whatnot. You know what I mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;rewards-curiosity-etc&quot;&gt;Rewards, Curiosity, Etc.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, this is kinda bullshit. We know that the brain’s behavior can be explained well by other simple concepts such as reward-maximization, curiosity, etc. But in my opinion, these can still be described in the aforementioned framework. Curiosity can be a part of the inconsistency elimination process given that the agent have the ability to generate elements in its world-view that were not observed before per se, and thus the agent might feel like it has the need to verify the modified—but in some parts imaginary—world-view that it now has. Also, I think that reward-maximization is a subset of inconsistency elimination. Reward-maximization is a special case when the agent sees that it wants the rewards, but it is not a special case when the agent might see itself as not deserving of the reward or avoiding it for some psychological reason (and thus some rewards could be conditioned by the self to paradoxically evoke negative feelings as well). In fact, in most cases, inconsistency elimination and reward-maximization are synonymous to each.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;~&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the end, I think that what the agent wants depends on genetic needs as well as goals created through the process of maintaining the consistency of a world-view. This is the agent-driven (internal) dynamics. As for the environment-driven (external) dynamics, lower total energy along a trajectory is preferred, which gives rise to conciseness. Thus, the intelligent agent will minimize the extent in which the constraints of the environment are violated (consuming the lowest energy) while maximizing the consistency of its world-view (achieving best accuracy). Consistency and conciseness might even be two faces of the same coin.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdulla Jasem Almansoori</name></author><summary type="html">The idea of a world view in AI is very important. If you want to simulate an autonomous agent that interacts with the world in a non-trivial manner, then we can say that the agent has to maintain a “world-view”.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Stupid Analysis of Intelligence</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/10/14/Intelligence.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Stupid Analysis of Intelligence" /><published>2021-10-14T02:18:19+04:00</published><updated>2021-10-14T02:18:19+04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/10/14/Intelligence</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/10/14/Intelligence.html">&lt;p&gt;Intelligence is a relative property in the sense that one is more intelligent if: 1) one has “truer expectations” about the world, 2) one converges towards such expectations using a “shorter path”, i.e. with a lesser amount of action or work. The definition can be more meaningful by introducing more dimensions through deconstructing the two properties of intelligence to more layman terms, especially the second property of action. For example, we can compare the intelligence of two agents in a constrained action space (e.g. limited time, resources, etc). What about “truer expectations”? What does it actually mean?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of expectation as the realization of a world event. It depends on the way we model these things in our brains. “Truthiness” here is measured based on the difference between the “expected” realization (the world-view we had, so to speak) and the “actual” realization (the thing that actually happened and is part of history now). So, in this sense, “truthiness” itself is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; necessarily the “truth” because it is solely based on &lt;em&gt;the perspective in which this “actual realization” is observed and stored as data&lt;/em&gt;. However, in the limit of truthiness, we can have only two values (or directions to go to): true or false (or 1 and 0, doesn’t matter). In other words, if we are certain about the truthiness of an event, then we can know for sure whether our expectations are true or false because of boolean logic. This is the case where the axioms in math are absolutely true events by nature of construction, so “expectations” are logical and follow given an implication or a reduction mechanism. Errors are absolute and uncertainties are nonexistent in this framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you introduce uncertainties, you can always go back to more fundamental, certain piece of knowledge from which your current knowledge follows. Then, you can reconsider it and slightly adjust it in order to find a truer body of knowledge overall. This is similar, in a broad sense, to when Einstein discovered a more general (and truer, in this sense) theory than Newton’s. (It is also kinda similar to backpropagation). In fact, Newton’s theory is true for almost all everyday-life physics, but Einstein’s theory is true for strictly more situations than Newton’s is. Nonetheless, Newton is still considered to be very intelligent—maybe not any less intelligent than Einstein, so it is not only about truthiness here, it is also about having the truest expectation by consensus of what truthiness constitute of (for example, at the time of Newton, his theory was the truest form of a physical theory), as well as who was the first and quickest to have such expectations and communicated them efficiently. This can be applied on so many levels, but in this example the definition of intelligence is applied in a broad sense.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, but does communication constitute intelligence? One could argue that some savants have the ability to see and understand things that normal humans cannot possibly fathom. Sure, it might be interesting to ponder the fact that “the theory of everything” might be in someone’s brain right now who will never be able communicate it to us, for example, but we simply cannot measure what we do not observe, so that someone might remain as seemingly-non-intelligent as they were before the theory of everything came to their mind. Thus, communication should constitute “observable” intelligence, or rather observable anything really. (Well, unless we can decode brain signals for that matter).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Consider this intelligence comparison test between two agents. We assume that both scenarios are identical except for the brains of the agents. We put each agent on an identical and non-trivial island. The agent that survives longer wins, but we cannot observe anything until the game finishes, i.e. one agent dies. The more intelligent agent is supposed to survive longer (on average, roughly speaking). However, the agents did not have to communicate anything in order for us to deduce who is more intelligent. Therefore, communication does constitute intelligence but not in the restricted sense of normal human communication. We can generalize communication to include the usage of any media to convey information. However, the agent can convey information regarding its own intelligence by its actions, such as its survival, but it does not have to. This means that there are simple facts about the universe that we may never be able to observe, including the extreme intelligence of the guy who discovered the theory of everything in his garage but couldn’t convey it to anyone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intelligence is a complicated concept to define rigorously. I’m trying to define intelligence in the broadest sense possible as a relative property in terms of two quantities: truthiness and action. Truthiness could be described as the “consistency with respect to some prior knowledge”, and action could be described as “the amount of work done, or planned to be done, in order to achieve such consistency”. Then, intelligence is the extent in which an agent can be more consistent with less action. It is further desirable to describe intelligence with respect to solving a specific category of problems, such as solving physics and math problems vs. solving a social problem with your company. In this manner, we can refine the definition of intelligence for specific instances of behavior given some explicit constraints on the setting.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdulla Jasem Almansoori</name></author><summary type="html">Intelligence is a relative property in the sense that one is more intelligent if: 1) one has “truer expectations” about the world, 2) one converges towards such expectations using a “shorter path”, i.e. with a lesser amount of action or work. The definition can be more meaningful by introducing more dimensions through deconstructing the two properties of intelligence to more layman terms, especially the second property of action. For example, we can compare the intelligence of two agents in a constrained action space (e.g. limited time, resources, etc). What about “truer expectations”? What does it actually mean?</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Free Doom of Speech</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/01/FreeDoomOfSpeech.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Free Doom of Speech" /><published>2020-12-01T02:18:19+04:00</published><updated>2020-12-01T02:18:19+04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/01/FreeDoomOfSpeech</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/01/FreeDoomOfSpeech.html">&lt;p&gt;Freedom of speech is having the right to voice whatever opinion you have. You feel powerful by voicing any opinion you have (and if you have Twitter, you are invincible and can win any argument). It doesn’t feel fair to have your voice censored. You want to be heard because the other person is heard, so why not you? It is only fair to be equal to that other person, right? We want to believe that we are all the same, have the same rights, and deserve the same treatments. Equality is optimal in some sense. If we assume that people want to have the maximum amount of rights but no less than any other person out there, then equality is the only way to do that. Therefore, we feel like it’s only fair to have the right to voice our opinion as much as the other person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Free doom of speech is the phenomenon that follows precisely when the evil desires of society start to manifest in some parts. Humans are constantly on the run looking for opportunities to gain an advantage to achieve what they desire. It is an instinct. They want to hunt better than you to get that sweet T-Rex fillet mignon. They want to be more powerful than you to get stuff from you and then settle in your land and live in your house and then, you know, do bad stuff to you. They want to get more money than you because they want more stuff than you because you’re ugly and stupid. It is all about the advantage, the power. Call it what you want, but humans are competing for that very thing they desire in every waking moment, and things can get really nasty and ugly really quick, just like it used to be in the past where wars were commonplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowadays, humans have achieved a more mature understanding of moral values that “make sense” and help humans make fair decisions in their daily lives. Thus, we have come to understand the kinds of decisions that are considered “evil” that we should avoid, even though those evil acts could let us gain an advantage in getting what we desire. Have you ever stolen a piece of candy as a little kid? You might have, and you are not to be blamed for it because you still didn’t understand the idea of morality very well. You would think that gaining such an “unfair” advantage (i.e. not having to pay for candy while others have to pay) is an opportunity that you should seize to achieve what you desire. The major problem with this is that gaining an advantage for yourself alone might cause an unfair disadvantage for a lot of others. This is why morality is good. It is there to help regularize the decisions of people such that they will not cause severe, unfair disadvantages to others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know what you’re thinking. How the fuck does this have anything to do with freedom of speech? Well, the connection is quite subtle, but from the subtlety comes the doom of this “free” kind of speech (as in, you-don’t-have-to-pay-for-candy free). The evil created within society by the lack of morality will eventually create opportunities of abuse in our freedom of speech. People will use freedom of speech itself to gain an unfair advantage by claiming its power of freedom and censoring others from it! For example, I can say this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“It is my freedom to say whatever I want. Fuck you. You are such a stupid racist xenophobic bigot cunt that should just die right now. No, actually, you should slowly rot in hell alone while crying bloody streams of misery. No wait, scratch that. You should slowly rot to death in a muddy hole in the middle of a burning black forest while the hounds of hell devour your guts like it’s their birthday, all while an elephant is ramming you non-stop. Oh hey, it is my freedom of speech! You and I have the same power and we both shall exercise our rights to voice our free opinions! Sure, the devil might be jealous of my spiteful unholiness and rotten morals, but I have like 10k retweets and 67k likes on my previous post, so I am invincible.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Have we really forgot that fairness and equality of rights is what lies at the heart of freedom of speech? How come those who use their speech to cancel others are still feeling completely fair about it? Clearly, morality is not a natural law as it only makes sense when humans view themselves functioning as a part of a society that wants to improve “as a whole” (without ignoring the least well-off). But morality can also be a selfish law if one wants it to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe one of the main causes of “cancel culture”, which is a more polished sub-term of “free doom of speech”, is that people hold different moral values, to the point where they can actually think that a person they disagree with deserves to die (which is the most severe, almost-always-unfair disadvantage anyone can get). This is the most evil form of of an unfair disadvantage that you can impose on others using the privileges of freedom of speech. That is how the “freedom” of one person turns into the “free doom” of another. That is the state of freedom of speech nowadays. SAD!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdulla Jasem Almansoori</name></author><summary type="html">Freedom of speech is having the right to voice whatever opinion you have. You feel powerful by voicing any opinion you have (and if you have Twitter, you are invincible and can win any argument). It doesn’t feel fair to have your voice censored. You want to be heard because the other person is heard, so why not you? It is only fair to be equal to that other person, right? We want to believe that we are all the same, have the same rights, and deserve the same treatments. Equality is optimal in some sense. If we assume that people want to have the maximum amount of rights but no less than any other person out there, then equality is the only way to do that. Therefore, we feel like it’s only fair to have the right to voice our opinion as much as the other person.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Barely Legal</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/09/BarelyLegal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Barely Legal" /><published>2020-11-09T02:15:15+04:00</published><updated>2020-11-09T02:15:15+04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/09/BarelyLegal</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/09/BarelyLegal.html">&lt;p&gt;For all \(\epsilon &amp;gt; 0\), suppose that the following happens:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\(18+\epsilon\) year-old guy: “hi ur very attrektive can u be my gf?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;\(18-\epsilon\) year-old girl: “Ewww, creep! Get away from me you pedo!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For infinitely small \(\epsilon\), you can see the absurdity of this rejection, as the age difference would be \(2 \epsilon\), and as you might already know, you can find \(\delta &amp;lt; 2\epsilon\), where \(\delta\) is… you know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyways, creeping out from an arbitrary threshold set heuristically by the law is in itself absurd, as the law’s primary intent is to encourage moral behavior, order, and justice. This is a classical case of overfitting to the law. We are overfitting to the model of morality and justice, so we need a regularizer of some kind. We need to tax these mf pedos!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdulla Jasem Almansoori</name></author><summary type="html">For all \(\epsilon &amp;gt; 0\), suppose that the following happens:</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Memes Are Things</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/29/MemesAreThings.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Memes Are Things" /><published>2020-06-29T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2020-06-29T00:00:00+04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/06/29/MemesAreThings</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/06/29/MemesAreThings.html">&lt;p&gt;Memes are just an easily reproducible “signal” that communicates a certain relatable idea or thought. Memes could come in many forms, including words, pictures, videos, gestures, face expressions, or any other signal that we can “get”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it. There is nothing special about memes. They are only ubiquitous for the very fact that their definition is so ambiguous and vague, they occupy an extremely large variety of signals that we consume daily. People are hesitant to call certain jokes “memes” because they want to reserve that common notion of memes to something else that was born out of the images-with-captions kind of memes, but that’s not always representative of memes as we know them. I believe I can give a (somewhat) comprehensive definition of (Internet) memes because I lived through some of the early eras of the Internet (90s + 00s). Let me give you some examples of what I think are memes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, I think being Rick Roll’ed is one of the most classic memes on the Internet. Dramatic animals are also memes. The notion of “trolling” was extremely meme-worthy since everybody experienced it and already get it, so it was turned into one of the most famous memes and probably marked the transition to modern day memes. Dad jokes are also memes. Why not? You could easily create a dad joke meme by writing a dad joke on an image of a man who looks like the typical funny-wannabe dad. You can even generalize dad jokes that way and call them “dad memes”. (Go ahead, you don’t even have to give me credits for it.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of the early memes that even preceded trolling memes—and in fact catalyzed their growth—are the images-with-captions kind of memes, which are simply images with funny two-liner jokes, with the second line being the punchline (and the first line being an introductory mundane line, or an intriguing title, or something like that). It’s just a joke with a punchline that you can’t tell without showing the image. It’s an image joke, sort of. The image can be reused if it vaguely or absurdly describes a situation that happens a lot (think stock photos), and so the meme could be reproduced abstractly without showing the image itself. Just mentioning the meme’s name in the right situation is enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One more complicated example is the following. Sometimes your friend does something unique that only he/she/it does. Let’s say your stupid friend likes to say something cheesy like “cool beans” or “awesome sauce”. You could easily create a “meme” out of that, not in the usual sense but abstractly. You have an abstract image of the funny fact that your friend uniquely and repeatedly says this stupid line. You know that whenever your friend does that thing, everybody who’s aware of the situation would unconsciously form that abstract image, so if you follow it with a punchline and complete the picture, your would form an abstract form of a meme that occupy space and time! Ok skip the space and time part, I mean a meme that is delivered in a abstract, non-static form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My point is that &lt;strong&gt;memes are a generalization of jokes&lt;/strong&gt;, encompassing other complex social constructs (such as rhetoric). Memes are usually fun, or at least relatable, because you simply can’t create a boring meme. I mean, it was interesting to whoever created it at the very least. Also, some things look like memes but aren’t. For example, depending on your definiton, “&lt;em&gt;Stay calm and carry on&lt;/em&gt;” is not a meme in and of itself, but a meme could easily be—and was, in fact—created out of it. To make my idea clearer, I will provide some characteristics of jokes that are highly in common with memes, which memes seem to cover in a more general sense:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Relevance&lt;/strong&gt;. Jokes and memes both work well when the consumer is a person who is aware of the main content in a way that make them ready to consume the punchline or receive the material as expected from the producer. Relevance could also be thought of as “agreeability”.
    &lt;ol&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Truthiness&lt;/strong&gt;. The truth of the material presented increases agreeability and validity. (Actually, when you think more carefully about it, truthiness is correlated with relevance but less general as a characteristic, so truthiness is not really necessary but quite common in memes and jokes alike).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Absurdity&lt;/strong&gt;. The more absurd or unexpected the punchline, the higher the “fun factor”, which is a factor that correlates with attention, and thus interactiveness, eventually leading to agreeability. It could be said that absurdity helps pump up the relevance of the content, much like how controversial opinions often get a larger share of attention than it should.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ol&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Communicability&lt;/strong&gt;. Memes should be easily communicated. If you create a meme that is 10-pages long, or a meme that is a 30-min gif, then it’s going to fail as a meme or even be recognized as one. Though it could still be a meme to your (naive) eyes. That also falls within the realm of rhetoric and consensus of thoughts.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reproducibility&lt;/strong&gt;. Memes should be easily reproducible. That’s why we’re having a ton of images-with-captions in the social media era. Images became very easily reproducible, and now we’re seeing a surge of gif-able memes because gifs started to become easily reproducible as photo-editing and photo-sharing softwares became more accessible and powerful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interesting thing about memes is that they behave like organisms. Yes, we can actually study the dynamics of memes by modeling them as abstract organisms with some weird survival strategies. Basically, you can model them like this: memes are ideas that continue to exist based on their relevance (fitness) in their host environments (humans), and can reproduce as information in abstract media (e.g. bits, files, images, gifs in computers, and thoughts, gestures, and memory) and communicated by the hosts via these media. Notice that this model involves all three characteristics of jokes. The most important variable here is relevance, as it dictates how the memes will survive and what communication channels and reproduction methods they will be found attracted to. In fact, the communicability and reproducibility of a meme could also have a direct impact on the relevance of the meme to the host itself, so relevance is , you know, very “relevant”. Also, notice that all these variables are completely out of the memes’ control, but those who study memetics religiously will disagree and say that “Memes are gonna take over the world!” Nah.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I remember taking a class at USC by Leonard Adleman, who is a pretty well-known computer scientist. Well, if you recognize the name, you might immediately think “Wow! I would love to be taught cryptography by a professor like him.” Nope, the class wasn’t on cryptography, and no he didn’t teach us about the RSA encryption at all. In fact, the class was about memes! Prof. Adleman was interested in studying (a more general notion of) memes and why they behave like organisms. He thought that a theory similar to Darwin’s survival theory could be hypothesized about memes. He was aiming too high, to be quite frank.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea that memes are like genes is not new, and, in my humble opinion, it shouldn’t be revived or pursued any further, except perhaps for some mind gymnastics. What’s new about what I have presented here could be seen as the opposite of what those endeavors are seeking to prove—that memes are simple, not grand, not omnipresent, not fundamental, and not anything of that kind. Memes are like “things”. Things are everywhere. They are the building blocks of our lives and universe, and you can’t refute this argument. Do you know why? Because a “thing” is so abstract and vague, it could possibly describe anything. Heck, it’s right there in the sentence I wrote! Of course, a &lt;strong&gt;thing&lt;/strong&gt; could describe any&lt;strong&gt;thing&lt;/strong&gt;, what else would it describe then. In the same spirit, memes are vague, so a precise study or theory about memes is very likely doomed to fail (i.e. fail to predict or to explain) no matter how accurate it is. Studying memes is like studying things. Your theory could be about anything, and it would still be correct, because anything is still a thing, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look, memes are simple. And they’re vague. Don’t overcomplicate them. If you wish to study memes any further, please do so for the philosophical fun and not for anything serious. Otherwise, your endeavors will be aimless and futile. Bye.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdulla Jasem Almansoori</name></author><summary type="html">Memes are just an easily reproducible “signal” that communicates a certain relatable idea or thought. Memes could come in many forms, including words, pictures, videos, gestures, face expressions, or any other signal that we can “get”.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">You Don’t Understand I-Don’t-Understand</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/12/18/YouDontUnderstandIDontUnderstand.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="You Don’t Understand I-Don’t-Understand" /><published>2019-12-18T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2019-12-18T00:00:00+04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/12/18/YouDontUnderstandIDontUnderstand</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/12/18/YouDontUnderstandIDontUnderstand.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a pedagogical analysis of not-understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Teachers often ask students things like this: “Did you understand?”, “Do you have any questions?”, or “Who can answer this question?”, and so on. The problem with this kind of questions is that the teacher is giving the student control over the lecture, and quite often the students are very bad at making the lecture interesting or useful, unless the audience is a small number of extremely interested and cooperative students, like in some graduate courses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Depending on the students, the assumed goal of every lecture is well-known; to successfully communicate novel ideas. However, sometimes, the students’ goal is to finish the lecture as soon as possible, disregarding how much they actually understood (i.e. how much of the ideas were communicated successfully). This is typical due to a lot of reasons, many of which can be attributed to having different priorities that make one pay less attention to the lecture. For example, if the student was playing a video game and have been fighting a tough boss for a long time and not winning, the student might sit during the lecture brainstorming new strategies to beat this tough boss, in addition to—unsuccessfully, of course—trying to understand the material of the lecture. This is the first point to keep in mind: students may be present, but their minds may be stuck somewhere else. They should be in the context of the lecture and paying good attention to be able to understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now the second point is about the “understanding” part. When a student says “Yes, I understand”, they probably don’t understand in &lt;em&gt;your&lt;/em&gt; sense, they understand in &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; (probably naive) sense. They might have understood the subject to the extent that enables them to barely pass the next exam, which is a really bad measure of understanding. A key measure of understanding some concept is the ability to explain it (the Feynman definition of understanding). This is a really good measure to test not only the students’s understanding but your own understanding as well. Of course, since you’re the teacher, you‘d better understand the topic you’re explaining. Now, instead of asking “Do you understand?”, you can ask “Can you explain it?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The final point is related to the second in that you try to get into the students’ heads and teach them from there. Don’t let them decide whether things are going well based on their own ways. Whenever you ask a question, ask it not in the sense that you are proof-checking their answers and trying to beat them into failure, but in the sense that you want them to &lt;em&gt;voluntarily&lt;/em&gt; contribute their answers to the lecture. For example, the students might not have any follow-up question, in which case you can stir up their internal reasoning until an apparent contradiction or a missing piece of the puzzle prompts the students to ask interesting questions, and thus remember the concept from the memory of this internal conflict, so to speak. Questions are a good way to test student’s understanding as well, especially open-ended ones. Let them ask interesting questions and let them find the answers themselves by guiding them only when necessary. Do it from their perspectives, not yours.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you prepare the students to be able to understand, communicate, apply, and expand on an idea, they will thus be able accelerate the progress of science and spread of knowledge further down the road in their careers.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdulla Jasem Almansoori</name></author><summary type="html">This is a pedagogical analysis of not-understanding.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Arrogant Rationalism</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/12/13/ArrogantRationalism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Arrogant Rationalism" /><published>2019-12-13T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2019-12-13T00:00:00+04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/12/13/ArrogantRationalism</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/12/13/ArrogantRationalism.html">&lt;p&gt;Scientists possess more scientific knowledge than the average human. It is implied by the job title itself—scientists, those who “do science” for a living. But science is the thing that contains all known logical knowledge about the universe. Hence, scientists often think that they know more about how the world works, which is kinda true. They also tend to be more logically consistent by the very facts that they are doing science and that science must be logically consistent because without logical consistency, one might as well claim anything one wants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is usually the case that science, which is largely based on rational thinking and the scientific method, is a superior school of thought compared to traditional ones in almost all disciplines. There is something so useful about science that makes people from everywhere adopt it to solve their problems. It’s probably related to its ability to predict and explain an outcome of a phenomenon based on a logically consistent model of that phenomenon. Problem solving, basically. More often than not, this ability makes scientists believe that they have some sort of a bestowed authority on topics that require logical reasoning. They believe that they can always make better decisions and solve problems more efficiently. In a way, they’re right. However, experience and guts can triumph over meticulous logical reasoning sometimes, so scientists do fail—naively so in some cases. But seriously, why do scientists with their superior rational thinking and the acclaimed scientific method ever fail? Well, I believe scientists fail because either: 1) their logically consistent model is inherently wrong, or (this is usually the case) 2) their models don’t apply to the real world very well, which also invalidates some of their explanations about why the modeled phenomenon happened.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a mode of thinking where scientists or rational people hold very tightly and dearly to their “beautiful” theories, which turn out to be prone to naive failures in hindsight. I like to call that &lt;em&gt;arrogant rationalism&lt;/em&gt;. Since this mode of thinking is adopted by a wider subset of people that encompass &lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; scientists, I will refrain from simply using the vague term “&lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; scientists” to describe these people. Instead, I will use the term “arrogantly-rational people” as it is more self-descriptive. These people are implicitly arrogant in their assertions and think that the opinions of the non-scientifically-oriented community is, well, bullshit-ish, so to speak. In other words, they think their opinons are based on lies, norms, biases, and/or emotions. These people might use (pseudo-)science to over-analyze every phenomenon, thinking that their scientifically-sound assumptions are often valid and make sense in the real world. They comment on every topic, thinking that the scientific method and logical consistency of &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt; world model can solve everything. Unfortunately, life is never that simple. The model that works today for you might not work tomorrow, and some systems are just too damn complex to explain using a few explanatory variables (especially and particularly systems that involve human decisions, which includes stock markets, for example).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most humans eventually make (a lot of) subtle mistakes in their logical reasoning. Sometimes, decisions based on simple hands-on experience can beat the shit out of the classical scientific method when used naively. There is nothing wrong with science, it’s just that, sometimes, it is difficult to &lt;em&gt;do science&lt;/em&gt; correctly and apply it to the real world, at least at the current state of science. Think about the science of &lt;em&gt;love&lt;/em&gt;, for example, and how useless it might be (I may be wrong though). Maybe one day we will find a rigorous scientific theory of love that let us make reliable predictions and marry people to each other efficiently so that everyone can be happy, but right now, nah. I don’t think any scientific model of love would cut it in the real world. This is exactly one of these topics where experience would pat science on the back and say: “Step back, buddy”. In general, rational thinkers face this hurdle when they try analyze complex social phenomena based on logic alone because these phenomena include things like emotions that might come up as unexplainable, complex randomness that might siginificatly impact the model’s outcome (again, stock markets is a good example, which is why sentiment analysis is gaining tract in algorithmic trading). When we reach the level where we can scientifically model the human brain exactly, experience might then be explained away from within this model and thus be beaten by any rational thinking based on this model, arrogant or not. For now, such a model seems to be quite far-fetched from the current reality of science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So when should arrogantly-rational people stop being overly confident about their theories and experiments? In my opinion, it is healthy to criticize oneself every now and then and assume that one is wrong, and then revalidate one’s own views. Sometimes, the people who are not making any sense to you right now might actually be making a lot of sense when you look at it from a different perspective. Just start with their mindset and come to their conclusions from there, and maybe you will find something along the way. And if you didn’t, well… just move on. There will always be wrong people out there, and you don’t always have to convince everybody on the planet that your world model is more sound and logically consistent than theirs. Remember, your world model might be only true in your mindset alone and not necessarily in others’. You will never &lt;em&gt;completely understand&lt;/em&gt; other people. Don’t be &lt;em&gt;arrogantly&lt;/em&gt; rational, be &lt;em&gt;wisely&lt;/em&gt; rational.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdulla Jasem Almansoori</name></author><summary type="html">Scientists possess more scientific knowledge than the average human. It is implied by the job title itself—scientists, those who “do science” for a living. But science is the thing that contains all known logical knowledge about the universe. Hence, scientists often think that they know more about how the world works, which is kinda true. They also tend to be more logically consistent by the very facts that they are doing science and that science must be logically consistent because without logical consistency, one might as well claim anything one wants.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Deep Success</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/12/12/DeepSuccess.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Deep Success" /><published>2019-12-12T00:00:00+04:00</published><updated>2019-12-12T00:00:00+04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/12/12/DeepSuccess</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/12/12/DeepSuccess.html">&lt;p&gt;The most troubling trend in with the way of life of some of the most successful people is that they optimize their lives for success (&lt;em&gt;duh&lt;/em&gt;), but success itself is a quality that is measured by some standards other &lt;strong&gt;people&lt;/strong&gt; set. You can’t simply claim that you are successful because you see yourself so. It can definitely happen, but it’s gonna be pathetic and sad as we all know. You have to make people decide whether you are successful or not. So being successful does not make sense without relying on people’s opinions. Whose opinion you rely on is something that only you can decide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you rely on your own opinion, then you will very likely end up having delusions of grandeur or commit suicide. If you rely on society’s opinion, then you might end up living like a robot; going through a pre-defined life of typical, boring success. Both options are viable, but something in between ought to hit the sweet spot where you can find the perfect mix of satisfying internal opinions (one’s validation of oneself) and external opinions (others’ validation of oneself).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at it this way, we are just trying to satisfy everybody’s definition of success—including ours, of course—to varying degrees that depend on complex social relationships. For example, satisfying your family is more important than satisfying a bunch of strangers you saw on the street who wants you to pay for their bus ticket home. The more attached you are to a group of people, the more you want to satisfy their standards of success and seek their validations. People who fall in love, for example, might do some crazy stuff just to seek the validation of their potential partners (i.e. crush) or loved ones since they are very strongly attached to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem of achieving &lt;em&gt;success&lt;/em&gt; in the sense that one is living life &lt;em&gt;correctly&lt;/em&gt; (to some extent) requires a healthy mix of validations from many reliable sources. But the older one gets, the smaller the list of external validations one needs. At the end, you will only care about yourself (and perhaps your partner), so success, as others see it, wouldn’t mean shit to you. Your definition of success would be to live through your daily routine as accurately as possible without any interruptions or distractions. In fact, many people regret not spending time with their families (and especially their parents) in their youth, no matter how successful they become. They regret it because their definition of &lt;em&gt;success&lt;/em&gt;, as in succeeding to live a &lt;em&gt;good life&lt;/em&gt;, has changed with time and become less concerned with materialistic achievements and mere number games. Success becomes more complex and deep, and starts to signify something deeper, more long-term, and more meaningful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all, meanings are subjective, and what success means to you may be completely different to another. In fact, that other person might be you in the future. So which kind of success should one thrive to achieve? Think about people who die young, for example. They won’t regret the fun they had and the non-responsible actions they took during their short lives (e.g. smoking and doing drugs, disrespecting people, not following the rules, bad relationship with family, etc.). It is true that they died young, which is an inevitable “failure” that successful people always try to avoid (as in, they try to stay alive as long as possible). However, their death might have had nothing to do with what they did (e.g. they died in a airplane crash). Therefore, we can safely say that they actually lived a fun, albeit short, life without consequences, and that’s something you can call success! (Unless they really preferred to live a longer life, of course, but they died, so…) If you knew you were gonna die young, what kind of successful life would you prefer? Will you still seek fame and money? Will you commit crimes for your own satisfaction if you were to die tomorrow? Or will you cherish your last moments with the people you love the most? What really makes you choose the path you take? And would your view of success change by knowing a little bit of the future and why?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are (biologically) similar in the way they think, so they usually form similar opinions, but that doesn’t make the different opinions any less “correct”. I can convince myself that success is all about gaining more knowledge, and treat success in every context by that definition, and therefore, aim to gain more knowledge, disregarding money, happiness, and love, which are things that consitute other people’s whole lives. Nobody can prove me wrong; it’s just that my opinion is a radical one and yours is a general one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People are social creatures, they are not programmed to live alone. Words like “success” and “fame” do not really make sense in non-social settings, so their meanings are deeply intertwined with they way society perceive those labels and use them. So what is really meant by “deep success” or “meaningful life”? I believe it boils down to the way society views the idealistic individual, where society is a group of people living together and sharing resources (and thus, interact non-trivially by altering others’ welfare). The collection of views converge to the average successful individual in society (with the whole collective group bias, of course), but radical (i.e. outlier) views of success can possibly exist within large subgroups as well, though with a smaller probability as the subgroup gets larger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can tell, we can’t conclude anything of substantial value about the secrets of deep, meaningful success. This is because there are no secrets, only subjectivity and ambiguity. Nonetheless, I will end this essay with my humble opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be successful is to live happily (convinced and content with your current state of affairs), sufficiently (have enough resources to maintain your current state of affairs), and actively (play a non-trivial role in society by interacting with other’s state of affairs). You have to be, overall, convinced that your life is good. It might seem exaggerated in simplicity, but it is not. Money helps, but it isn’t really success as we all know; it’s just merchandise with special consensus-based superpowers. Fame is easy to achieve without being successful (do something extremely stupid in public. Boom. You’re famous). Sex gets boring after a while (look at all the hot celebrity couples getting divorced). What remains is your own (long-term) progress in life and how content you are with it. The three conditions I gave ensure that you are happy and can stay happy in a non-trivial manner (interacting with people ensures that you are not being deluded into a lonely hole of idiosyncratic happiness, so it is a certificate or a validation of happiness that our curious brains seem to need).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, if your path in life is a happy path, and the people you care about can certify that in their actions, and perhaps most importantly, that &lt;strong&gt;you are convinced and content with your life&lt;/strong&gt;, then I think you pretty much succeeded in life. The Internet-generations experience enormous amount of stress and anxiety in their social lives because they might evaluate and validate their own happiness based on an extremely large pool of not-so-positive opinions and ideologies (i.e. the Internet), so they are under constant pressure to achieve an unrealistic form of success. They key is to be convinced that your life is happy, or otherwise, to work towards a reasonable goal and be content with as little as possible. There is nothing wrong with not being the best or not doing or seeing everything. The curiosity of the mind could lead it to the stars of sucess or to the depths of misery, irrespective of strong will and meticulous planning. It is your luck in life, or as Void from Berserk said “&lt;em&gt;Everything is within the flows of Causality&lt;/em&gt;”.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdulla Jasem Almansoori</name></author><summary type="html">The most troubling trend in with the way of life of some of the most successful people is that they optimize their lives for success (duh), but success itself is a quality that is measured by some standards other people set. You can’t simply claim that you are successful because you see yourself so. It can definitely happen, but it’s gonna be pathetic and sad as we all know. You have to make people decide whether you are successful or not. So being successful does not make sense without relying on people’s opinions. Whose opinion you rely on is something that only you can decide.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Truman Show Syndrome</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2019/10/22/TrumanShowSyndrome.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Truman Show Syndrome" /><published>2019-10-22T03:46:55+04:00</published><updated>2019-10-22T03:46:55+04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2019/10/22/TrumanShowSyndrome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2019/10/22/TrumanShowSyndrome.html">&lt;p&gt;If you know the movie &lt;em&gt;The Truman Show&lt;/em&gt;, then you know what I’m talking about, and you’ve seen this &lt;em&gt;syndrome&lt;/em&gt; before. I’ve personally seen it a lot in my life. Guess where? LA, the land of Hollywood, baby.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people act as if they are being constantly filmed by an invisible camera through their whole lives. But unlike Truman, they know they’re being filmed, and, again, unlike Truman, the hidden cameras don’t exist. So why did I call it The Truman Show Syndrome? Well… I don’t know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In any case, please don’t be like that. People who do that are annoying and self-centered. I feel like these kind of people like to post a lot of selfies on Instagram. In particular, they like to post a sequence of slightly perturbed selfies (for example, one selfie with a smile, one selfie without a smile, repeat with slightly different angles, black and white etc). Yes, we get how cool you look in all of these angles, and we did notice that the first selfie is slightly different than the second one, yet they both convey a different level of coolness that we have to be aware of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s not coincidence that this type of behavior is prevalent in Hollywood. Have you noticed that some actors like to act what they want to be? For example, some actors like to act in roles in which they are strong, sexy, beautiful, badass, and heros because &lt;em&gt;they want to be exactly that&lt;/em&gt;. These actors always act the same roles because &lt;strong&gt;they’re not really acting, they’re just being themselves&lt;/strong&gt;. They have a cool character in real life, and they just adapt it to new settings with different backstories. They don’t like to be in roles in which they are not cool (this is why there aren’t that many uncool Hollywood actors). Remind me of a role in which Brad Pitt portrayed a loser. Even loser roles in Hollywood are transformed in the context of the film into a cool role! Have you seen Jonah Hill in 21 Jump Street, for example? Rebecca Wilson, etc. One obvious example that I also have to mention is The Rock. He’s a very famous actor because he’s The Rock, not because he’s a great actor (which is not a bad thing to say about him, per se). I don’t even remember when he started acting. I used to like The Rock since WWF. He was my favorite wrestler because I thought he was really cool (have you smelled what The Rock was cooking?) Well, I guess some people are just so damn lucky that their personas are so like-able, they can gain money by simply existing. In fact, this seems to be true for existence itself. Losers don’t have as many friends as cool people because nobody wants to see more of losers and less of cool people, so cool people tend to have more opportunities and easier time in their lives. Same for Hollywood. Who wants to see a movie about a loser who didn’t do anything significant in their lives? The problem is that we are categorizing people into “cool people” and “loser people”. Some people actually watch movies for the &lt;em&gt;acting&lt;/em&gt;, believe it or not! Acting as in accurately portraying a role from a novel or from history no matter how uncool that role is. However, seems like nowadays we only want to see movies about cool people, so Hollywood movies tend to be biased toward cool culture. A movie about a loser can be a masterpiece, but it will surely be boring except for movie critics who appreciate good acting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how does this relate to &lt;em&gt;The Truman Show Syndrome&lt;/em&gt;? Well, it’s about the very thin line between &lt;em&gt;acting&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;being&lt;/em&gt;. We act everyday because of social norms and personal goals. It is very natural to behave differently depending on the context. It’s as if we are projecting our &lt;em&gt;selves&lt;/em&gt; on a 3D screen, poetically speaking. Consider this scenario: what if you wake up tomorrow realizing that you used to be the head of the largest secret criminal organization in the world, and your brain was, in fact, erased temporarily and timed to retreive its memories on this very day. And let’s say you found papers and proofs to make it even more dramatic. You have two options now: 1) &lt;em&gt;act&lt;/em&gt; like you were before coming into this weird realization and not embrace your true self, living your everyday life like you used to, ignoring the &lt;strong&gt;fact&lt;/strong&gt; that you are not truly the person you are &lt;em&gt;acting&lt;/em&gt; like right now (i.e. you are not truly the normal, boring person you are acting like), or 2) embrace your true self and &lt;em&gt;not act&lt;/em&gt;, which is itself &lt;em&gt;acting like you’re not acting&lt;/em&gt; until you completely adapt to your criminal overlord personality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We all have images of ourselves in our heads, and it feels like this body is only a medium for our minds to act in this world, so we will always &lt;strong&gt;act&lt;/strong&gt; what we are and what we want to be. The only difference with actors is that they try to “wake up” in a movie ready to embrace their newly realized, imaginary selves.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Abdulla Jasem Almansoori</name></author><summary type="html">If you know the movie The Truman Show, then you know what I’m talking about, and you’ve seen this syndrome before. I’ve personally seen it a lot in my life. Guess where? LA, the land of Hollywood, baby.</summary></entry></feed>